Guide to the NYU Abu Dhabi Capstone Archives AD.MC.004
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
- Science Division Projects, 2014-2021
  - Chemistry
    - Egbunu, Gabriel. Thermodynamic Characterization of HK3, 2021; 2021-0083 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2021-0083)
      Tumor cells utilize a high glycolytic flux known as the "Warburg effect" to sustain their high proliferation rates. The activation and further metabolism of glucose are initiated by hexokinase, a focal point of metabolic regulation. Hexokinase 2 (HK2) is significantly overexpressed in many cancer types and hence, it is a vital point in the development of inhibitors. The human hexokinase 3 (HK3) is not significantly overexpressed in tumors. However, biochemical differences in HK2 and HK3 could be exploited in improving the potency and specificity of current HK2 inhibitors. Here, we report the thermodynamic characterization of HK3. Experimental results reveal that both the melting temperature and calorimetric enthalpy change of wild-type HK3 are higher than for HK2. The identification of structural and biochemical differences between HK2 and HK3 could potentially be used in the development of new and more effective cancer therapies.
      Author provided keywords:
  - Computer Science
    - Spalveri Kruse, Anthony Matteo. Online Feedback Profiles for Digital Privacy Awareness, 2014; 2014-0042; 128 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2014-0042)
      Major: Computer Science
      Abstract: The public is largely unaware that third-party trackers actively collect their data. In turn, the application of data mining and machine learning to utilize this data is largely a mystery to users without a background in information technology. This paper proposes the use of a built-in browser application that actively collects user data and renders it to create a privacy feedback profile to the user. The feedback page focuses on informing users that third parties can monitor their data, along with making inferences on the user so they're aware of how telling their data can be. In a weeklong study, users of the application showed increased levels of concern and awareness for their digital privacy. These results encourage the use of such applications as viable ways of educating individuals and encouraging safer online browsing habits.
      Information technology; Internet; Data mining; Privacy
    - Grishin, Oleg. Displayer. A System for Democratizing Interactive Public Displays, 2015; 2015-0039; 3414 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2015-0039)
      Abstract: Many public spaces, including university campuses, have an abundance of public screens displaying information relevant to a particular site, such as upcoming events, student work showcases, general announcements, infographics and other relevant media. Displayer focuses on proposing and implementing an easy-to-use system that provides a front-end interface to create and schedule tasks that include but are not limited to displaying pictures, videos and slideshows. While many of such public screens focus on simply displaying information, the proposed system also allows for creating more interactive tasks, e.g. a video-portal between two displays. The project discusses a working implementation of such a system, while also outlining possible future extensions, e.g. connecting systems like the Microsoft Kinect to allow the creation of more complex tasks, such as signing up for events by showing a student ID. While the working implementation performs a variety of those simple tasks, the system's back-end is built around the idea of allowing future (possibly user-written) extensions.
      Computer systems; Information display systems; Calendars; Computers
    - Shin, Jiwon. Reaching Out to You (in my own ways)., 2016; 2016-0039; 7965; Reaching Out to You (in my own ways) is a multimedia art project comprised of three pieces of artwork that individually combine analog and digital ways of communication in order to prompt the viewers to think about how the level of engagement changes according to different ways of communication. The artworks introduce analog and digital interventions to explore the formation and interaction of human relationships and suggest new ways of communication by intertwining both methods together. This project provides spaces in which viewers can compare the analog and the digital methods used in each of the artworks in delivering the intended messages in the most genuine way. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2016-0039)
      Reaching Out to You (in my own ways) is a multimedia art project comprised of three pieces of artwork that individually combine analog and digital ways of communication in order to prompt the viewers to think about how the level of engagement changes according to different ways of communication. The artworks introduce analog and digital interventions to explore the formation and interaction of human relationships and suggest new ways of communication by intertwining both methods together. This project provides spaces in which viewers can compare the analog and the digital methods used in each of the artworks in delivering the intended messages in the most genuine way.
    - Aytemiz, Batu. In Game Assistance Methods, 2017; 2017-0024; One of the most important factors when it comes to making a multiplayer competitive game is ensuring that players are evenly matched. When skill differences are extreme, weaker players become frustrated and there is not enough of a challenge for the stronger player to stay engaged. Earlier papers on the topic establish that assisting weaker players works extremely well in reducing the score differences. In this paper we explored different types of assistance methods and specifically their effects on player enjoyment and perceived competence. Overall we see that assistance methods very significantly reduce the score disparity and affect several aspects of their gameplay experience. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2017-0024)
      One of the most important factors when it comes to making a multiplayer competitive game is ensuring that players are evenly matched. When skill differences are extreme, weaker players become frustrated and there is not enough of a challenge for the stronger player to stay engaged. Earlier papers on the topic establish that assisting weaker players works extremely well in reducing the score differences. In this paper we explored different types of assistance methods and specifically their effects on player enjoyment and perceived competence. Overall we see that assistance methods very significantly reduce the score disparity and affect several aspects of their gameplay experience.
    - Onyibe, Chukwuyem. Sentiment Analysis in Tweets, 2017; 2017-0025; This capstone project is about the detection of sentiment and stance in individual tweets. The task encompasses two subfields in Natural Language Processing: Sentiment Analysis and Stance Detection, both of which are related. The main objective is to use the Conditional Random Fields, the statistical modelling method, to build a system(s) that automatically determines from a tweet, with high efficiency, an author's general sentiment or sentiment towards a given target. Every iteration of the system is tested against a gold standard to gauge its efficiency. The reason for the use of CRFs is test how it fairs in non-sequential data classification tasks. The approach is feature-based, improved by optimized CRF parameters. A set of lexical feature combinations are tested and the top scoring feature combinations is tested again with sets of CRF parameter value combinations. The top scoring values, combined with the top scoring lexical features make up the system for dataset in question. The results show that CRFs perform well at non-sequential classification. Moreover, if sequential context are added to these tweets (i.e. tweets in a conversation thread), the efficiency of CRFs increases. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2017-0025)
      This capstone project is about the detection of sentiment and stance in individual tweets. The task encompasses two subfields in Natural Language Processing: Sentiment Analysis and Stance Detection, both of which are related. The main objective is to use the Conditional Random Fields, the statistical modelling method, to build a system(s) that automatically determines from a tweet, with high efficiency, an author's general sentiment or sentiment towards a given target. Every iteration of the system is tested against a gold standard to gauge its efficiency. The reason for the use of CRFs is test how it fairs in non-sequential data classification tasks. The approach is feature-based, improved by optimized CRF parameters. A set of lexical feature combinations are tested and the top scoring feature combinations is tested again with sets of CRF parameter value combinations. The top scoring values, combined with the top scoring lexical features make up the system for dataset in question. The results show that CRFs perform well at non-sequential classification. Moreover, if sequential context are added to these tweets (i.e. tweets in a conversation thread), the efficiency of CRFs increases.
    - Stara, Zbynek. Spatial Distortion Approach to Traffic Congestion Visualization, 2017; 2017-0039; The field of traffic congestion visualization relies heavily on colorcoded topographical maps; little work has been done, however, to examine the merits and possible weaknesses of this approach, and to evaluate its performance in comparison to alternative visualizations. This paper presents a new approach to visualization of traffic congestion that uses spatial distortion instead of color to present traffic information in a fundamentally different manner. A user study was employed to empirically evaluate the ability of each of the two visualization approaches to influence the users' routing decisions in a given traffic network. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2017-0039)
      The field of traffic congestion visualization relies heavily on colorcoded topographical maps; little work has been done, however, to examine the merits and possible weaknesses of this approach, and to evaluate its performance in comparison to alternative visualizations. This paper presents a new approach to visualization of traffic congestion that uses spatial distortion instead of color to present traffic information in a fundamentally different manner. A user study was employed to empirically evaluate the ability of each of the two visualization approaches to influence the users' routing decisions in a given traffic network.
    - Terai, Koh. Autofocus System for Cinematic Applications., 2017; 2017-0031; Unlike video camcorders, phone cameras, point-and-shoot, and DSLRs, cameras and lenses used for cinema do not come with any autofocus capabilities. Instead, a dedicated person on a film set (the focus-puller) is in charge of manually measuring the distance from the camera to the subject and focusing the lens. Although this allows for complete artistic control over the focus, there are situations in which perfect focus is hard to achieve by focus-pullers (e.g. actors missing their positions, actors moving around within their positions) or a situation in which having a dedicated focus-puller is difficult (e.g. budgetary constrains, tight spaces). This project will attempt to design and create an autofocus system that will aid the focus-pullers to get the right focus through the use of software and hardware development. This intuitive system should be able to out perform inexperienced focus-pullers as well as making focus pulling easier for certain environments such as low contrast and dark locations. Our current prototype of the system is slow but relatively accurate and functional as an initial proof of concept. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2017-0031)
      Unlike video camcorders, phone cameras, point-and-shoot, and DSLRs, cameras and lenses used for cinema do not come with any autofocus capabilities. Instead, a dedicated person on a film set (the focus-puller) is in charge of manually measuring the distance from the camera to the subject and focusing the lens. Although this allows for complete artistic control over the focus, there are situations in which perfect focus is hard to achieve by focus-pullers (e.g. actors missing their positions, actors moving around within their positions) or a situation in which having a dedicated focus-puller is difficult (e.g. budgetary constrains, tight spaces). This project will attempt to design and create an autofocus system that will aid the focus-pullers to get the right focus through the use of software and hardware development. This intuitive system should be able to out perform inexperienced focus-pullers as well as making focus pulling easier for certain environments such as low contrast and dark locations. Our current prototype of the system is slow but relatively accurate and functional as an initial proof of concept.
    - Abalo, Jacqueline; Andrew Callender, Cristhian Munoz, Jaehurn Nam, and Mark Surnin. Structure Identification in PDF Documents, 2018; 2018-0095 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0095)
      Up until the present day, there has not been a reliable, consistent, and easily available tool with which to identify and extract structural elements within documents. This is due to the fact thatPDFs do not conform to any conventions in terms of document structure and that PDF generators tend to use different rules for assembling the documents. A solution that can allow users to retrieve structured information from a document in a form that is easily manipulated can have a noticeable positive impact for professionals across a broad spectrum of industries.The framework put forward in this paper,Texture, uses diverse heuristic techniques in order to extract structural elements (lists, titles, headers and footers, paragraphs, figures and tables) fromPDFs. They are assigned different weights that lead to robust and accurate extractors.Texture also introduces a domain specific language that allows users to query documents using natural language.We demonstrate that Texture has potential to perform as well as the manual labeling process while being much easier to use than any labor crowdsourcing platform. Texture is also cheaper, quicker, and more scalable than hiring crowd workers to handle the same extraction tasks.
    - Ahmad, Muaz; Dana Abu Ali, Hayat Al Hassan, Ming Hu, Paula Dozsa. Time-offset Interaction Application, 2018; 2018-0101 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0101)
      This paper presents a bilingual (Arabic-English) interactive human avatar dialogue system. The system is named TOIA (time-off set interaction application), as it simulates face-to-face conversations between humans and digital human avatars recorded in the past. TOIA is similar to a conversational agent, or chatbot, but differs in that it is based on an actual human being and can be used to preserve and tell stories. The system is designed to allow anybody, simply using a laptop, to create an avatar of themselves, thus facilitating cross-cultural and cross-generational sharing of narratives to wider audiences. It also supports cross-lingual dialogues in Arabic and English.
    - Hayat, Hashim. Esfera: A Scalable peer-to-peer video broadcasting architecture overlaying WebRTC, 2018; 2018-0068 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0068)
      Due to the increasing accessibility of the Internet, and live video streaming platforms like YouTube and Facebook, the demand for live video broadcasting is growing rapidly. Public figures, news channels, and sports event with followers numbered in millions receive up to a million views in their livestreams and the number is growing. The current broadcasting infrastructures rely on large and expensive networks of media servers and edge caches that are distributed around the globe to maintain network efficiency, quality, and reliability. In this paper, we present Esfera, a light-weight, scalable, peer-to-peer live video broadcasting infrastructure that utilizes the potentials of WebRTC, a set of APIs that allows ultra-low latency browser-to-browser communication without external plugins. Commercial platforms such as Facebook Messenger, and Google Hangouts have successfully tested and deployed their VoIP services on WebRTC, and broadcasting is the next milestone in the success of WebRTC. In this paper, we provide a detailed analysis of the design and implementation of Esfera and present an evaluation of its performance. Finally, we discuss the limitations and future challenges that are posed by peer-to-peer live broadcasting using WebRTC.
    - Hopkins, Brooke. Insulin Pump Vulnerabilities and Design for Secure Device Communication, 2018; 2018-0073 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0073)
      Advanced health technology promises to bring considerable advances to patient care. However, there are great security risks which can have disastrous health consequences. Several studies show that implantable medical devices (IMDs) have vulnerabilities enabling man in the middle attacks that could disclose patient data or even inflict patient harm. Insulin delivery systems, which are commonly used IMDs, are vulnerable for this reason. All communication between the continuous glucose monitor (CGM) and the insulin pump is unencrypted, and protective PINs are passed in plain text. While there is existing research that documents this vulnerability and proposes solutions, these provide only suggestions for device modification that could be implemented by the manufacturer in future models. In this paper, we propose a design for a fully backwards compatible external device that ensures authenticity and integrity of communication between the CGM and the insulin pump. The design employs friendly jamming techniques to provide access control by jamming unauthenticated communication.
    - Jensen, Frederik. On Problems Related to Epsilon-Nets, 2018; 2018-0081 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0081)
      This capstone presents results on problems related to epsilon-nets in the plane; a method to approximate a set of data points with a small number of points. We contribute to the literature by improving the bounds for several simple cases. Speci cally, we obtain a tight lower bound of 2/3 on two-point strong epsilon-nets with respect to both halfspaces and disks closing two open problems in the literature. We also obtain tight bounds for all k-sided objects in the dual setting for nets of size 1, and a tight bound of 2/3 for nets of size 2 with respect to halfspaces. We show the two following elegant results: Given a set of points and a set of disks in the plane, if every three disks intersect in a common input point, then two of those points hit all disks; and, given a set of points and a set of halfspaces in the plane, if every three points belongs to a halfspace then two halfspaces cover all points.
    - Joshi, Aadi. Epsilon-nets and related problems, 2018; 2018-0067 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0067)
      Given a family of geometric objects S and a set of points P, we would like to prove that all object s in S that contain more than a certain fraction, epsilon, of points in P, can be hit by a small number of points in a set called the epsilon-net. By this we mean that if an object s in S contains more than a fraction epsilon of the points in P, then the object must also contain one or more of the points in the epsilon-net. In this capstone paper, we explore a variety of problems related to epsilon-nets. We improve the bounds on epsilon for disks and half-spaces when the epsilon-net contains 2 points. We also improve the bounds for disks and half-spaces for dual epsilon-nets. There are two additional proofs we provide related to hitting sets. We prove that if every three points is contained in a half-plane, then two half-planes must cover all points. We also prove that if every three disks intersect at a point, then two points hit all disks.
    - Chen, Wei Peter; Shehroze Khan, Jihyun Kim, Tarik Zulfikarpasic. Qutr: A Cross-lingual Messenger with Keyword Searchable Phrases for the Travel Domain, 2018; 2018-0089 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0089)
      We present Qutr (Query Translator), a smart cross-lingual communication application for the travel domain. It is a real-time messaging app that automatically translates conversations while supporting keyword-to-sentence matching. Qutr relies on querying a database that holds pre- translated phrases in different languages with the use of keywords. The application addresses common cross-lingual communication issues such as translation accuracy, speed, personalization and privacy.
    - Csapo, Gabor. Classifying face representations with noise tolerant deep learning, 2018; 2018-0054 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0054)
      Many massive sociological studies could be enabled by efficient machine learning on large scale online dataset. The main problem in the domain is that classification requires uniform data with accurate labels, but online collected image datasets can not provide pose, illumination or resolution invariance and the assigned labels have a high error rate. We surveyed the current state-of-the-art methods in generating face representations from online datasets, and tested them with noise resistant machine learning architectures. We applied the findings on a dataset of 30 million images to aid research at Princeton University on racial discrimination in career progression in corporate structures. Our final architecture: From the input images we generate low level face representations using the Openface neural network to overcome the invariance in our dataset. These representations are then fed into a base neural network which has a denoising layer attached to it that attempts to correct the error in the labels. Our approach reached 0.79 f1-score on the FERET dataset. The novelty of the project is two-fold: it adds to our understanding of machine learning under noisy conditions, and proposes a computationally efficient approach to classify millions of faces.
    - Mirza, Muhammad Shujaat. Reimagining Privacy in Online Social Networks, 2018; 2018-0093 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0093)
      There has been growing interest in the field of longitudinal exposure of the user's publicly available data on social media platforms. While the privacy of current postings has been the subject of multiple research groups, the re-evaluation of the privacy settings for these posts down the line is a new area of interest for people. In regard to recent episodes such as the Facebook Cambridge Analytica scandal, discussions have revolved around the value we associate with the old postings. Whereas different platforms try to offer options to have some control over the accessibility of our information, their effectiveness relies on the extent to which users understand those options. Through this study, we aim to explore the relation between user's perception of their profile privacy settings and their actual settings. Our study, based on the participant pool of 91, reports that there is a significant mismatch between the actual exposure to the posts versus the user's perception of the privacy settings. We also investigate the impact old postings can have on friend circle expansion. The findings show how the aged information, relevant or irrelevant, finds a way to influence the user's behavior in the current context.
    - Moore, Megan. Detection and Analysis of Devices Used to Censor Networks, 2018; 2018-0060 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0060)